PROFESSOR: In the last section, we
introduced modern cryptography schemes
and discussed the difference between
symmetric and asymmetric keys.
We saw that cryptographic algorithms based
on symmetric keys have a conundrum when
it comes to key distribution namely,
how can we securely exchange the keys if we don't yet
have them in our possession to encrypt
the initial transmission?
The answer as we saw, is to use public-key cryptography based
on asymmetric keys, that is, using
a public key for encryption and a different private key
for decryption.
The keys are related to one another mathematically
and their associated information security
relies on it being computationally
impractical to determine the private key
even when you know the public key.
This is achieved through the use of mathematical one-way
functions, where the ease of use of the cryptosystem
is based on the mathematical simplicity of implementing
the function in the forward direction
and its security is based on the mathematical complexity
of implementing it in the reverse or inverse direction.
And so now in this section, we'll
take a look at a specific quintessential example
of public-key cryptography, the RSA cryptosystem,
and discuss the fundamentals of how it works.
And again, we'll discuss communication
in the context of Alice and Bob in the presence
of an eavesdropper, Eve.
Bob would like to send a secure message to Alice
and so he requests her public key which we'll represent here
with the letter E, and he uses it to encrypt his plain text
message, which we'll call m and generate an unreadable
ciphertext called C. Alice retains her private key
D, which she uses to decrypt the ciphertext she receives
from Bob, and thereby reconstruct
the original plain text message.
Although Eve has access to the public key and the ciphertext,
she can't decrypt it to reconstruct the plain text
message because she doesn't have access
to the private decryption key.
And because the two keys are mathematically
related to one another through a one-way function,
computing the private key from what Eve has in hand
is by design a very hard problem to solve
on a classical computer.
The RSA cryptosystem is based on a mathematical concept called
modular exponentiation.
The basic idea is that one can efficiently
define three large positive integers, e, d, and N, such
that the following expression is true for all integers m
between 0 and N. Namely, n raised to the power e
and then raised again to the power d is equal to itself
modulo N. And it's very hard for a computer
to calculate the number d even when given the numbers e and N.
Now, this is a fantastic result because it
says that Bob can generate ciphertext
by taking a plain text message, converting it to an integer
m using an agreed-upon protocol, and then raising m
to the power e using the public encryption key.
Then Alice can decrypt the ciphertext
by raising it to the power d to obtain back the number m modulo
N from which she can reconstruct the plain text message.
So the public key comprises the numbers e and N
and the private key comprises the numbers
d and N. Now, strictly speaking, only d needs to be kept private
but Alice will need both d and N to do the decryption.
With this background, the RSA cryptosystem
can be broken into four steps, key generation,
key distribution, encryption, and decryption.
Let's take them one at a time, key generation starts
with finding two distinct prime numbers p and q, a task which
can be performed efficiently on a classical computer
using mathematical protocols called primality tests.
Prime numbers are those that are divisible by only themselves
and unity, and importantly, these numbers
must be chosen at random.
And we'll learn later in the course more
about how quantum mechanics can, in principle generate
true randomness.
For now, though, let's just assume
that we use a pseudo-random number generator
on a classical computer.
Next, the prime numbers p and q are multiplied together
to generate the number N. Multiplication, of course,
is also efficient on a classical computer.
The number N is used as the modulus
for both the public and private keys
in the performance of modular exponentiation.
The next step is to determine the encryption and decryption
keys themselves, e and d.
This is done using the periodicity property
of modular exponentiation.
To see this, let's consider a simple example,
we'll take the number 3 and its exponents modulo 10, so 3
to the i-th power modulo 10, where i is an integer, 1, 2, 3,
et cetera.
We see that 3 to the first power modulo 10 is 3,
3 squared modulo 10 is 9, 3 cubed is 27 and so 3
cubed modulo 10 is 7.
The modulo 10 is the remainder when dividing 27 by 10.
So 27 divided by 10 is 2 with a remainder 7.
Next, 3 to the fourth power is 81, which modulo 10 is 1.
And continuing on, we see that the numbers repeat 3, 9, 7, 1,
3, 9, 7, 1, and so the periodicity here is 4.
We'll call this periodicity r, so r equals 4 in this case.
Now, there's a relationship between the periodicity r
and the prime numbers p and q.
Consider a general sequence, x modulo N,
x squared modulo N, x cubed modulo N, et cetera.
Where N equals p times q and x is a number that
is not divisible by p or q.
Then the sequence has a period r that evenly divides p minus 1,
times q minus 1.
Let's see how this plays out in our above example.
There the modulus is N equal 10, which
has prime factors p equal 2 and q equals 5, 2 times 5 equals
10.
Then p minus 1 is 1, and q minus 1 is 4,
thus the quantity p minus 1, times q minus 1 is 1 times 4,
and that equals 4.
And this evenly divides the period r equals 4.
So that checks.
What's important here is that this is essentially
our one-way function.
If we're given prime numbers p and q,
then we can calculate the periodicity r.
We won't go into how this is done here,
we just note that it can be done efficiently
on a classical computer.
Again, if we know the prime numbers p and q.
However, if we're just given N but we don't know p and q,
it's a hard problem to find the periodicity r.
And typically the periodicity is a very large number,
not like the simple example given here.
So a brute force search is not efficient either.
So returning to key generation, Alice
has prime numbers p and q, she used
them to determine the period r and she keeps
all of these numbers private.
She now uses r to determine the keys e and d.
First, she chooses an integer e in the range 3
to r that is also co-prime with r, that is, e and r have
no common divisor other than 1.
Now, often this number is simply chosen so that it's not too big
and has mostly 0s to enable efficient encryption.
For example, 2 to the 16th power plus 1
equals 65,537, which in binary is 1 followed
by 15 zeros and another 1.
This is the public encryption key e.
Then the private decryption key is directly calculated
from the expression d times e, equals 1 modulo r.
In summary, Alice generated the public encryption
key e and the private decryption key d from the periodicity r
based on randomly chosen prime numbers p and q
which multiply together to yield N. Alice keeps
private the integers p, q, and r, which she used to calculate
her private decryption key d.
In contrast, the encryption key e and the number
N can be made public.
In the next step, key distribution,
Alice sends Bob the public encryption key e
and the number N. Bob has a plain text
message that he wants to securely transmit to Alice.
He first turns his message into an integer N
using an agreed-upon reversible protocol called padding scheme.
He then computes the ciphertext c using modular exponentiation
and the public key, c equals m to the e-th power modulo N.
Bob then sends the ciphertext to Alice,
Alice then applies for decryption key d
to the ciphertext.
Using modular exponentiation once more, c to the d-th power,
Alice calculates the result, m modulo N.
And by reversing the padding scheme
Alice recovers the original plain text message.
Again, the security of the RSA cryptosystem
is based on the use of a one-way function.
In this case, the challenge of period finding and modular
exponentiation.
As we just saw, if one knows the prime factors p and q,
then one can efficiently find the modular exponentiation
period r and thus generate encryption keys e and d.
However, if we're just given the modulus N,
there's no known efficient classical algorithm
that lets us find its prime factors p and q,
and so there's no efficient means to determine the period
r under these conditions.
Thus, even if we reveal the modulus
N and the public encryption key e,
there's no known efficient means for Eve
to calculate the private key d, that
is on a classical computer.
In the next section, we'll look at Shor's algorithm
and discuss how period finding can be efficiently performed
on a quantum computer, thus enabling
in principle, an efficient pathway to breaking the RSA
cryptosystem.